<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The true lavv of free monarchy, or The reciprocall and mutuall duty betvvixt a free king and his naturall subjects. By a well affected subject of the kingdome of Scotland.</title>
            <title>True lawe of free monarchies</title>
            <author>James I, King of England, 1566-1625.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78586</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J145</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E238_23</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6414</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872985</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872985</idno>
            <idno type="VID">158234</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78586)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 158234)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 41:E238[23])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The true lavv of free monarchy, or The reciprocall and mutuall duty betvvixt a free king and his naturall subjects. By a well affected subject of the kingdome of Scotland.</title>
                  <title>True lawe of free monarchies</title>
                  <author>James I, King of England, 1566-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by T.P. in Queens-head-Alley in Pater noster-row,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An edition of: King James I.  True lawe of free monarchies, 1598.</note>
                  <note>"Advertisement to reader" signed: C. Philopatus [i.e. James I, who signed the first edition: Philopatris].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Monarchy --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Political science --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Kings and rulers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:158234:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE TRVE LAVV OF FREE MONARCHY, OR THE RECIPROCALL and mutuall duty betvvixt a free KING and His natural Subjects.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a well affected ſubject of the Kingdome of</hi> SCOTLAND.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed, and are to be ſold by <hi>T. P.</hi> in <hi>Queens-head-Alley</hi> in Pater noſter-row, 1642.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:158234:2"/>
            <head>An Advertiſement to the Reader.</head>
            <p>ACcept, I pray you, (my deare Countrey-men) as thankfully this Pamphlet that I offer unto you, as lovingly it is written for your weale. I would be loath both to be faſchious and fectleſſe. And therefore, if it be not ſententious, at leaſt it is ſhort. It may be ye miſſe many thing that ye look for in it. But for excuſe thereof, conſider rightly that I only lay down herein the true grounds, to teach you the right way, without waſting time upon refuting the adverſaries. And yet I truſt, if ye will take narrow tent, ye ſhall find moſt of their great guns payed home again, either with contrary concluſions, or tacite objections, ſuppoſe in a dairned forme, and indirectly. For my intention is to inſtruct, and not irri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat, if I may eſchew it. The profit I would wiſh you to make of, it is, as wel ſo to frame all your actions according to theſe grounds, as may confirme you in the courſe of honeſt and obedient ſubjects to your King, in all times comming, as alſo, when ye ſhall fall in purpoſe with any that ſhall praiſe or excuſe the by-paſt rebellions, that break forth either in this Countrey or in any other, ye ſhall herewith be armed againſt their Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren ſongs, laying their particular examples to the ſquare of theſe grounds. Whereby ye ſhall ſoundly keep the courſe of righteous Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, diſcerning wiſely of every action, only according to the quality thereof, and not according to your prejudged conceits of the committers. So ſhall ye, by reaping profit to your ſelves, turne my paine into pleaſure. But leaſt the whole Pamphlet run out at the gaping mouth of this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, if it were any more enlarged: I end, with committing you to God, and me to your charitable cenſures.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>C. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:158234:2"/>
            <head>The true Law of free Monarchies, Or the reciprocke and mutuall duty betwixt a free King and his naturall Subjects.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S there is not a thing ſo neceſſary to be known by the people of any Land, next the knowledge of their God, as the right knowledge of their alleageance, according to the forme of Government eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed among them, eſpecially in a <hi>Monarchy,</hi> (which forme of Government, as reſembling the Divinity, approcheth neareſt to perfection, as all the learned and wiſe men from the beginning have agreed upon: Vnity being the perfection of all things) So hath the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and (which is worſe) the ſeduced opinion of the multitude blinded by them, who think themſelves able to teach and inſtruct the ignorants, procured the wrack and and overthrow of ſundry flouriſhing Common-wealths; and heaped heavy calamities, threatning utter deſtruction upon others. And the ſmiling ſucceſſe, that unlawfull rebellions have oftentimes had againſt Princes in ages paſt (ſuch hath been the miſery, and iniquity of the time) hath by way of practiſe ſtrengthned many in their error: albeit there cannot be a more decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable argument; then to judge by the juſtneſſe of the cauſe by the event thereof; as hereafter ſhall be proved more at length, And among others, no Common-wealth, that ever hath been ſince the beginning, hath had greater need of the true knowledge of this ground, then this our ſo long diſordered and diſtracted Common-wealth hath: the misknowledge hereof being the only ſpring, from whence have flowed ſo many endleſſe calamities, miſeries, and confuſions, as is better felt by many, than the cauſe thereof well known, and deeply conſidered. The natural zeale therfore, that I beare to this my native Country, with the great pity I have to ſee the ſo-long diſturbance therof, for lack of the true knowledg of this ground (as I have ſaid before) hath compelled me at laſt to break ſilence, to diſcharge my conſcience to you, my deare Countrymen herein, that knowing the ground from whence theſe your many endles troubles have proceeded, as well as ye have already too-long taſted the bitter fruits thereof, ye may by knowledge, and eſchewing of the cauſe eſcape, and divert the lamentable effects that ever ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily follow thereupon. I have choſen then only to ſet down in this ſhort Treatiſe the true grounds of the mutuall duty, and allegeance betwixt a free and abſolute <hi>Monarche,</hi> and his people; not to trouble your patience with anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the contrary propoſitions, which ſome hath not been aſhamed to ſet down in writ, to the poyſoning of infinite number of ſimple ſoules, and their own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall, and well deſerved infamy. For by anſwering them, I could not have eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewed whiles to pick, and bite well ſaltly their perſons: which would rather have bred contentiouſneſſe among the readers (as they had liked or miſliked) then ſound inſtruction of the truth. Which I proteſt to him that is the ſearcher of all hearts, is the only mark that I ſhoot at herein.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, I will ſet down the true grounds, whereupon I am to build, out of the Scriptures, ſince <hi>Monarchy</hi> is the true pattern of Divinity, as I have already ſaid: next, from the fundamentall Laws of our own Kingdome, which neareſt muſt concerne us: thirdly, from the Law of nature, by divers ſimilitudes drawn out of the ſame: and will conclude ſinne by anſwering the moſt waighty and appearing incommodities that can be objected.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:158234:3"/>
The Princes duty to his ſubjects is ſo clearly ſet down in many places of the Scriptures, and ſo openly confeſſed by all the good Princes, according to their oath in their Coronation, as not needing to belong therein, I ſhall as ſhortly as I can run through it.</p>
            <p>Kings are called <hi>Gods</hi> by the Propheticall King <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal 82.6.</note> becauſe they ſit upon God his throne in the earth, and have the count of their adminiſtration to give unto him. Their office is, <hi>To miniſter juſtice and judgement to the people,</hi> as the ſame <hi>David</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſal. 101. 2 King 18. 2 Chro 29. 2 Kin 22. &amp; 23.2.34, &amp; 35. Pſal 72 1 King. 3. Rom. 13. 1 Sam. 8. Ier 29.</note> 
               <hi>To advance the good, and puniſh the evill,</hi> as he likewiſe ſaith: <hi>To eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh good laws to his people, and procure obedience to the ſame,</hi> as divers good Kings of <hi>Judah</hi> did: <hi>To procure the peace of the people:</hi> as the ſame <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>To decide all controverſies that can ariſe among them,</hi> as <hi>Salomon</hi> did: <hi>To be the Miniſter of God for the weale of them that do well, and as the Miniſter of God, to take vengeance upon them that do evill,</hi> as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith. And finally, <hi>As a good Paſtor, to go out and in before his people,</hi> as is ſaid in the firſt of <hi>Samuel: That through the Princes proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity the peoples peace may be procured,</hi> as <hi>Jeremy</hi> ſaith.</p>
            <p>And therefore in the Coronation of our own Kings, as well as of every Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Monarch, they give their oath, firſt to maintain the Religion preſently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed within their Countrey, according to their laws, whereby it is eſtabliſhed, and to puniſh all thoſe that ſhould preſſe to alter, or diſturbe the profeſſion ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: And next, to maintain all the lowable and good laws made by their prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, to ſee them put in execution, and the breakers, and violaters thereof, to be puniſhed, according to the tenor of the ſame: And laſtly, to maintain the whole Countrey, and every ſtate therein, in all their ancient priviledges, and liberties, as well againſt all ſorraine enemies, as among themſelves: And ſhortly to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the weale and ſtouriſhing of his people, not only in maintaining and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to execution the old lowable laws of the Countrey, and by eſtabliſhing of new (as neceſſity and evill manners will require) but by all other meanes poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to foreſee and prevent all dangers, that are likely to fall upon them, and to maintain concord, wealth, and civility among them, as a loving father, ond care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full watchman, caring for them more than for himſelf, knowing himſelfe to be ordained for them, and they not for him; and therefore countable to that great God, who placed him as his lieutenant over them, upon the perill of his ſoule, to procure the weale of both ſoules and bodies, as far as in him lieth, of all them that that are committed to his charge. And this Oath in the Coronation is the clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, civill and fundamentall law, whereby the Kings office is properly defined.</p>
            <p>By the law of nature the King becomes a naturall Father to all his Lieges at his Coronation. And as the father of his fatherly duty is bound to care for the nouriſhing, education and vertuous government of his children: even ſo is the King bound to care for all his ſubjects. As all the toyle, and pain that the father can take for his children, will be thought light and well beſtowed by him, ſo that the effect thereof redound to their profit and weale: So ought the Prince to do towards his people As the kindly father ought to foreſee all inconvenients and dangers that may ariſe towards his children, and though with the hazard of his own perſon, preſſe to prevent the ſame: So ought the King toward his people. As the Fathers wrath &amp; correction upon any of his children, that offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, ought to be by a fatherly chaſtizment ſeaſoned with pity, as long as there is any hope of amendment in them: So ought the King towards any of his Lieges that-offends in that meaſure. And ſhortly as the fathers chif joy ought to be in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:158234:3"/>procuring his childrens well fare, rejoycing at their weale, ſorrowing and pity<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at their evill, to hazard for their ſafety, travell for their reſt, wake for their ſleep; and in a word, to think that his earthly felicity and life ſtandeth &amp; liveth more in them, nor in himſelfe: So ought a good Prince think of his people.</p>
            <p>As to the other branch of this mutuall, and reciprock band, is the duty and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leageance, that the Lieges owe to their King. The ground whereof, I take out of the words of <hi>Samuel,</hi> dited by Gods ſpirit, when God had given him comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement to heare the peoples voyce in chooſing and annointing them a King. And becauſe that place of Scripture being well underſtood, is ſo pertinent for our purpoſe, I have inſert herein the very words of the text.</p>
            <p n="9">9 <hi>Now therefore harken to their voyce: howbeit yet teſtifie unto them, and ſhew them the manner of the King, that ſhall raigne over them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10 <hi>So Samuel told all the words of the Lord unto the people that asked a King of him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11 <hi>And he ſaid, this ſhall be the manner of the King that ſhall raigne over you; he will take your ſons, and appoint them to his Charets, and to be his horſemen, and ſome ſhall run before his Charet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12 <hi>Alſo he will make them his Captaines over thouſands, and Captaines over fifties, and to eare his ground, and to reape his harveſt, and to make instruments of war, and the things that ſerve for his Charets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13 <hi>He will alſo take your daughters, and make them Apothecaries, and Cookes, and Bakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14 <hi>He will take your Fields, and your Vineyardes, and your beſt Olive-trees, and give them to his ſervants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15 <hi>And he will take the tenth of your ſeed, and of your Vineyards, and give it to his Eunuches and to his ſervants:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16 <hi>And he will take your men-ſervants, and your maid-ſervants, and the chiefe of your yong men, and your aſſes, and put them to his work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17 <hi>He will take the tenth of your ſheep: and ye ſhall be his ſervants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">18 <hi>And yee ſhall cry out at that day, becauſe of your King whom yee have choſen you: and the Lord will not heare you at that day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="19">19 <hi>But the people woull not heare the voyce of Samuel but did ſay: Nay but there ſhall be a King over us. <hi>20</hi> And we alſo will be like all other nations. and our King ſhall judge us, and go out before us, and fight our battels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="20">20 <hi>And we alſo would be like all other Nations, and our King ſhall judge us, and go out before us, and fight our battels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That theſe words and diſcourſes of <hi>Samuel</hi> were dited by Gods ſpirit, it needs no further probation, but that it is a place of Scripture, ſince the whole Scripture is dited by that inſpiration, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith: which ground no good Chriſtian will, or dare deny. Wherupon it muſt neceſſarily follow, that there ſpeeches proceeded not from any ambition in <hi>Samuel,</hi> as one loath to quite the reines that he ſo long had ruled, and therefore deſirous, by making odious the government of a King, to diſſwade the people from their farther importunate craving of one. For as the Text proveth it plainly, he then conveened them to give them a reſolute grant of their demand, as God by his own mouth commanded him, ſaying:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Harken to the voyce of the people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to preſſe to diſſwade them from that, which he then came to grant unto them, were a thing very impertinent in a wiſe man; much more in the Prophet of the moſt high God. And likewiſe, it well appeared in all the courſe of his life after, that his ſo long refuſing of their ſute before came not of any ambition in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:158234:4"/>him: which he well proved in praying, and as it were importuning God for the weale of <hi>Saul.</hi> Yea, after God had declared his reprobation unto him, yet he deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted not, while God himſelfe was wrath at his praying, and diſcharged his far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſute in that errant. And that theſe words of <hi>Samuel</hi> were not uttered, as a prophecy of <hi>Saul</hi> their firſt Kings defection, it well appeareth, as well becauſe we heare no mention made in the Scripture of any his tyranny and oppreſſion, (which, if it had been, would not have been left unpainted out therein, as well as his other faults were, as in a true mirrour of all the Kings behaviours, who it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth) as likewiſe in reſpect that <hi>Saul</hi> was choſen by God for his vertue, and meet qualities to govern his people: whereas his defection ſprung after-hand from the corruption of his own nature, and not through any default in God, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they that think ſo, would make as a ſtep-father to his people, inmaking wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully a choyce of the unmeeteſt for governing them, ſince the election of that King lay abſolutly and immediatly in Gods hand. But by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary it is plain, and evident, that this ſpeech of <hi>Samuel</hi> to the people, was to prepare their hearts before the hand to the due obedience of that King, which God was to give unto them; and therfore opened up unto them, what might be the intollerable quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that might fall in ſome of their Kings, thereby preparing them to patience, not to reſiſt to Gods ordinance, but as he would have ſaid. Since God hath gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted your importunate ſute in giving you a King: as ye have elſe committed an error in ſhaking off Gods yoke, and over-haſty ſeeking of a King: ſo beware ye fall not into the next, in caſting off alſo raſhly that yoke, which God at your ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ſute hath laid upon you, how hard that ever it ſeem to be. For as ye could not have obtained one without the permiſſion and ordinance of God: ſo may ye no more, fro he be once ſet over you, ſhake him off without the ſame warrant. And therfore in time arme your ſelves with patience and humility, ſince he, that hath the only power to make him, hath the only power to unmake him; and ye only to obey, bearing with theſe ſtraits that I now fore-ſhew you, as with the finger of God, which lyeth not in you to take off. And will ye conſider the very words of the Text in order, as they are ſet down, it ſhall plainly declare the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience that the people owe to their King in all reſpects.</p>
            <p>Firſt, God commanded <hi>Samuel</hi> to do two things; the one to grant the people their ſute in giving them a King; the other to forwarn them, what ſome Kings wil do unto them, that they may not thereafter in their grudging &amp; murmuring ſay; when they ſhall feele the ſnares here foreſpoken: We would never have had a King of God, in caſe, when we craved him, he had let us know how we would have been uſed by him, as now we find but over late. And this is meant by theſe words. <hi>Now therefore kearken unto their voyce; howbeit yet teſtifie unto them, and ſhew them the manner of the King that ſhall rule over them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And next, <hi>Samuel</hi> in execution of this commandement of God, he likewiſs doth two things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, he declares unto them, what points of Iuſtice and equity their King will break in his behaviour unto them. And next he putteth them out of hope, that, weary as they will, they ſhall not have leave to ſhake of that yoke, which God through their importunity hath laid upon them. The points of Equity that the King ſhall breake unto them are expreſſed in theſe words.</p>
            <p n="11">11 <hi>He will take your ſons, and appoint them to his Charets, and to be his hoſemen, and ſome ſhall run before his Charet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:158234:4"/>
12 <hi>Alſo he will make them his Captaines over thouſands, and Captaines over fifties, and to eare his ground, and to reape his harveſt, and to make instruments of war, and the things that ſerve for his Charets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13 <hi>He will alſo take your daughters, and make them Apothecaries, and Cookes, and Bakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The points of Iuſtice, that he ſhall break unto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, are expreſſed in theſe words.</p>
            <p n="14">14 <hi>He will take your Fields, and your Vineyardes, and your beſt Olive-trees, and give them to his ſervants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15 <hi>And he will take the tenth of your ſeed, and of your Vineyards, and give it to his Eunnches and to his ſervants: And alſo the tenth of your ſheep.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As if he would ſay, The beſt and nobleſt of your bloud ſhall be compelled in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh and ſervile offices to ſerve him. And not content of his own patrimony wil make up a rent to his own uſe out of your beſt lands. vineyards, orchards &amp; ſtore of cattell. So as inverting the law of nature and office of a King, your perſons and the perſons of your poſterity, together with your lands, and all that ye poſſeſſe ſhall ſerve his private uſe, and inordinate appetit. And as unto the next point (which is his forewarning them, that, weary as they will, they ſhall not have leave to ſhake off the yoake, which God through their importunity hath layd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them) it is expreſſed in theſe words.</p>
            <p n="18">18 <hi>And yet ſhall cry out at that day, becauſe of your King whom yee have choſen you: and the Lord will not heare you at that day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As he would ſay, When ye ſhall find theſe things in proof that now I ſorewarn you of, although you ſhall grudg and murmure, yet it ſhall not be lawfull to you to caſt it off, in reſpect it is not only the ordinance of God; bur alſo your ſelves have choſen him unto you, thereby renouncing for ever all priiviledges, by your willing conſent, out of your hands, wherby in any time hereafter ye would claim and call back unto your ſelves again that power, which God ſhal not permit you to do. And for further taking away of al excuſe, and retraction of this their cont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ract, after their conſent to underly this yoake with all the burthens that he hath declared unto them, he craves their anſwer, &amp; conſent to his propoſition: which appeareth by their anſwer, as it is expreſſed in theſe words.</p>
            <p n="19">19 <hi>Nay but there ſhall be a King over us.</hi> 20 <hi>And we alſo will be like all other nations, and our King ſhall judge us, and go out before us, and fight our battels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As if they would have ſaid; All your ſpeechs and hard conditions ſhall not skar us, but we will take the good and evill of it upon us, and we will be content to bear whatſoever but then it ſhall pleaſe our King to lay upon us, as well as other nations do. And for the good we will get of him in fighting our battels, we wil more patiently beare any burthen that ſhall pleaſe him to lay on us.</p>
            <p>Now then, ſince the erection of this Kingdom and <hi>Monarchy</hi> among the <hi>Iews</hi> and the law thereof may, and ought to be a patern to all <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and well foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Monarchies, as being founded by God himſelf, who by his Oracle, and out of his owne mouth gave the law thereof: what liberty can broyling ſpirits, and rebellious minds claim juſtly to againſt any Chriſtian <hi>Monarchy:</hi> ſince they can claime to no greater liberty on their part, nor the people of God might have done, &amp; no greater tyranny was ever executed by any Prince or Tyrant, whom they can object, nor was here fore-warned to the people of God, (and yet all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion countermanded unto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) if tyrannizing over mens perſons, ſons, daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and ſervants; redacting noble houſes, and men, and women of noble bloud, to ſlaviſh and ſervile offices; and extortion, and ſpoile of their lands and goods to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:158234:5"/>the Princes own private uſe and commodity, and of his courteours and ſervants, may be called a tyranny?</p>
            <p>And that this propoſition grounded upon the Scripture, may the more clearly appeare to be true by the practiſe oft proved in the ſame book, we never read, that ever the Prophets perſwaded the people to rebell againſt the Prince, how wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſoever hee was.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Samuel</hi> by Gods command pronounced to the ſame King <hi>Saul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.</note> that his Kingdom was rent from him, and given to another (which in effect was a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grading of him) yet his next action following that was peaceably to turn home, and with floods of tears to pray to God to have ſome compaſſion upon him.</p>
            <p>And <hi>David</hi> notwithſtanding he was inaugurate in that ſame degraded Kings room, not only (when he was cruelly perſecuted for no offence, but good ſervice done unto him) would not preſume, having him in his power, skantly, but with great reverence, to touch the garment of the annoynted of the Lord, and in his words bleſſed him:<note place="margin">1 Sam 2.4 1 Sam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> but likewiſe, when one came to him vanting himſelf untruly to have ſlain <hi>Saul,</hi> he without forme of proces, or tryall of his guilt, cauſed only for guiltineſſe of his tongue put him to ſodain death.</p>
            <p>And although there was never a more monſtruous perſecutor and tyrant than <hi>Achab</hi> was: yet all the rebellion, that <hi>Elias</hi> ever raiſed againſt him, was to fly to the wilderneſſe: where for fault of ſuſtentation, hee was fed with the Corbies. And I think no man wil doubt but <hi>Samuel, David</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> had as great power to perſwad the people, if they had liked to have imployed their credit to uprores and rebellions againſt theſe wicked Kings, as any of our ſeditious preachers in theſe dayes of whatſoever Religion, either in this Countrey or in <hi>France,</hi> had that buſied themſelves moſt to ſtir up rebellion under cloak of Religion. This far the only love of verity, I proteſt, without hatred at their perſons, have moved me to be ſomewhat ſatyrique.</p>
            <p>And if any will leane to the extraordinary examples of degrading or killing of Kings in the Scriptures, therby to cloake the peoples rebellion, as by the deed of <hi>Jehu,</hi> and ſuch like extraordinaries: I anſwer, beſides that they want the like warrant that they had, if extraordinary examples of the Scripture ſhal be drawn in dayly practiſe; murder under traiſt, as in the perſons of <hi>Ahud</hi> and <hi>Iael;</hi> theft, as in the perſons of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> comming out of <hi>Aegipt;</hi> lying to their parents to the hurt of their brother, as in the perſon of <hi>Iacob;</hi> ſhall all be counted as law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and allowable vertues, as rebellion againſt Princes. And to conclude, the practiſe through the whole Scripture proveth the peoples obedience given to that ſentence in the Law of God: <hi>Thou ſhalt not raile upon the Iudges neither ſpeak evell of the Ruler of thy people.</hi> To end then the ground of my propoſition taken out of the Scripture, let two ſpeciall and notable examples, one under the law, another under the Euangel,<note place="margin">Ie: 27.</note> conclude this part of my alled geance. Vnder the law, <hi>Ieremy</hi> threatneth the people of God with utter deſtruction for rebellion to <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzar</hi> the King of <hi>Babel,</hi> who althogh he was an Idolatrous perſecutor, a forrain King, a Tyrant, &amp; uſurper of their liberties; yet in reſpect they had once received &amp; acknowledged him for their King,<note place="margin">Ier. 29.</note> he not only commandeth them to obey him, out even to pray for his proſperity, adjoyning the reaſon to it; becauſe in his proſperity ſtood their peace. And under the Euangell that King, whom <hi>Paul</hi> bids the <hi>Romaines Obey</hi> and ſerve for <hi>conſcience ſake,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ie. 13.</note> was <hi>Nero</hi> that bloudy Tyrant, an infamy to his age, and a monſter to the world, being alſo an Idolatrous per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cutor, as the K. of <hi>Babel</hi> was. If then Idolatry &amp; defection fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, tyranny over their people, &amp; perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Saints, for their profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſake, hindred not
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:158234:5"/>the ſpirit of <hi>God</hi> to command his people under all higheſt paine to give them all due and hearty obedience for conſcience ſake, giving to <hi>Caeſar</hi> that which was <hi>Caeſars,</hi> and to God that which was Gods, as Chriſt ſaith, and that this practiſe throughout the booke of God agreeth with this law, which he made in the erection of that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie (as is at length before deduced) what ſhameleſſe preſumption is it to any Chriſtian people now a dayes to claime to that unlawfull liberty, which God refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to his own peculiar and choſen people? Shortly then to take up in two or three ſentences, grounded upon all theſe arguments, out of the Law of God, the duty, and alleageance of the people to their lawfull King, their obedience, I ſay, ought to bee to him, as to Gods Lievtenant in earth, obeying his commands in all things, except directly againſt God, as the commands of Gods Miniſter, acknowledging him a Judge ſet by God over them, having power to judge them, but to be judged onely by God, whom to only he muſt give count of his judgment; fearing him as then Judge loving him as their Father; praying for him as their Protector; for his continuance, he be good, for his amendment, if he be wicked, following and obeying his lawfull commands, eſchewing and flying his fury in his unlawfull, without teſiſtance, but by ſons and eares to God, according to that Sentence uſed in the Primitive Church in the time of the perſecution.</p>
            <p>Preces, &amp; Lachrymae ſunt arma Eccleſiae.</p>
            <p>Now as for the deſcribing the alleageance, that the heges owe to their Native King, out of the fundamentall and Civill Law, eſpecially of this Country, as I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, the ground muſt firſt be ſet down of the firſt manner of eſtabliſhing the Laws and forme of government among us: that the ground being firſt right layd, we may thereafter build rightly thereupon. Although it be true (according to the affirmation of thoſe that pride themſelves to be the ſcourges of Tyrants) that in the firſt begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Kings riſing among <hi>Gentiles,</hi> in the time of the firſt age, divers common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths and ſocieties of men chooſed out one among themſelves, who for his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and valour, being more eminent then the reſt, was choſen out by them, and ſet up in that roome, to maintaine the weakeſt in their right, to throw downe oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours, and to foſter and continue the ſociety among men; which could not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, but by vertue of that unity be well done yet theſe examples are nothing perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to us; becauſe our kingdom and diverſe other Monarchies are not in that caſe, but had their beginning in a far contrary faſhion. For as our Chronicles beare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, this, and eſpecially our part of it, being ſcantly inhabited, but by very few, and they as barbarous and ſcant of civility, as number, there comes our King <hi>Fergus,</hi> with a great number with him, out of <hi>Ireland,</hi> which was long inhabited before us, and making himſelfe maſter of the Country by his own friendſhip, and force, as well of the <hi>Ireland-men</hi> that came with him, as of the Country-men that willingly fell to him, he made himſelfe King and Lord, as well of the whole lands, as of the whole inhabitants within the ſame. Thereafter he and his ſucceſſours, a long while after their being Kings, made and eſtabliſhed their lawes from time to time, and as the occaſion required. So the truth is contrary in our ſtate to the falſe affirmation of ſuch ſeditious Writers, as would perſwade us, that the Lawes and ſtate of our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey were eſtabliſhed before the admitting of a King: whereby the contrary ye ſee it plainly proved, that a wiſe King comming among barbares, firſt eſtabliſhed the eſtate and forme of government, and thereafter made dawes by himſelfe, and his ſucceſſors according thereto.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:158234:6"/>
The Kings therefore in <hi>Scotland</hi> were before any eſtates or rankes of men with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſame, before any <hi>Parliaments</hi> were holden, or Lawes made: and by them was the Land diſtributed (which at the firſt was whole theirs) ſtates erected and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, and formes of government deviſed and eſtabliſhed. And ſo it followes of neceſſity, that the Kings were the authors and makers of the lawes, and not the lawes of the Kings. And to prove this my aſſertion more clearely, it is evident by the Roles of our Chancellery (which containe our eldeſt and fundamentall lawes) that the King is <hi>Dominus omnium bonorum,</hi> and <hi>Dominus directus totius Dominiy,</hi> the whole ſubjects being but his vaſſals, &amp; from him holding all their lands as their Over lord, who according to good ſervices done unto him, changeth their holdings from tacke to few, from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ord to blanch, erecteth new Baronies, and uniteth old, without adviſe or authority of either <hi>Parliament,</hi> or any other ſubalterin judicial ſeate. So as if wrong might be admitted in play (albert I grant wrong ſhould bee wrong in all perſons) the King might have a better colour for his pleaſure, without further reaſon, to take the land from his lieges, as over-lord of the whole, and doe with it as pleaſeth him, ſince all that they hold is of him: then, as fooliſh writers ſay the people might un-make the King, and put an other in his room. But either of them, as unlawfull, and againſt the ordinance of God, ought to be alike odious to be thought, much leſſe put in practiſe. And according to theſe fundamentall lawes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready alledged, wee daily ſee that in the <hi>Parliament</hi> (which is nothing elſe but the head Court of the King, and his vaſſals) the lawes are but craved by his ſubjects, and only made by him at their rogation, and with their adviſe. For albeit the K. make daily ſtatutes and ordinances, injoyning ſuch pains thereto as he thinks meet, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any adviſe of <hi>Parliament</hi> or eſtates; yet it lyes in the power of no <hi>Parliament,</hi> to make any kinde of law or ſtatute, without his Scepter be to it, for giving it the force of a law. And althogh diverſe changes have been in other Countries of the bloud Royall, and kingly houſe, the Kingdome being refectly conqueſt from one to another, as in our neighbour country in <hi>England,</hi> (which was never in ours) yet the ſame ground of the Kings right over all the Land, and ſubjects thereof remaineth alike in all other free <hi>Monarchies,</hi> as well as in this. For when the Baſtard of <hi>Normandie</hi> came into <hi>England,</hi> and made himſelfe King, was it not by force, and with a mighty army? Where he gave the Law, and tooke none, changed the laws, inverted the order of government, ſee downe the ſtrangers his followers in many of the old poſſeſſours roomes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this day well appeareth a great part of the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in <hi>England,</hi> being come of the <hi>Norman</hi> bloud, and their old Lawes, which to this day they are tuled by, are written in his language, and not in theirs. And yet his ſucceſſors have with great bappineſſe enjoyed the Crowne to this day. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the like was alſo done by all them that conqueſted them before.</p>
            <p>And for concluſion of this point, that the King is over-lord over the whole lands, it is likewiſe daily proved by the Law of our hoords, of want of Heires and of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtardies. For if a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oord be found under the earth, becauſe it is no more in the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or uſe of any perſon, it of the Law pertaines to the King. If a perſon, inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour of any lands or goods, dye without any ſort of heires, all his lands and goods returne to the King. And if a baſtard dye unrehabled without heires of his body (which rehabling only lyes in the Kings hinds) all that he hath likewiſe returnes to the King. And as yee ſee it manifeſt, that the King is Over-Lord of the whole
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:158234:6"/>Land: <hi>So is hee maſter over every perſon that inhabiteth the ſame, having power over the life and death of every one of them.</hi> For although a juſt Prince will not take the life of any of his Subjects without a cleare Law: Yet the ſame Lawes, whereby he taketh them, are made by himſelfe, or his predeceſſors. And ſo the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er flowes alwayes from himſelfe: As by daily experience we ſee, good and juſt Princes will from time to time make new lawes and ſtatutes, adjoyning the penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to the breakers thereof: which before the Law was made, had bin no crime to the ſubject to have committed. Not that I deny the old definition of a King, and of a law; which makes the King to be a ſpeaking Law, and the Law a dumb King: for certainely a King, that governes not by law, can neither bee countable to God for his adminiſtration, nor have a happie and eſtabliſhed Raigne. For albeit it bee true that I have at length proved, that the King is above the Law, as both the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, and giver of ſtrength thereto: yet a good King, will not onely delight to rule his ſubjects by the Law; but even will conforme himſelfe in his own actions ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, alwayes keeping that ground, that the health of the common-wealth be his chiefe Law. And where he ſees the Law doubt-ſome or rigorous, he may interpret or mittigate the ſame: leſt otherwiſe <hi>Summum jus</hi> be <hi>ſummairjuria.</hi> And therfore generall lawes, made publikely in Parliament, may upon knowne reſpects to the King by his authority be mittigated, and ſuſpended upon cauſes only knowne to him. As likewiſe, although I have ſaid, a good king will frame all his actions to be according to the Law: yet is hee not bound thereto but of his good will, and for good example giving to his ſubjects. For as in the Law of abſtaining from eating of fleſh in <hi>Lenton,</hi> the King will for examples ſake, make his own houſe to obſerve the Law: yet no man will think he needs to take a licence to eate fleſh. And although by our Laws, the bearing &amp; wearing of hag-buts, &amp; Piſtolets be forbidden, yet no man can unde any fault in the King, for cauſing his traine uſe them in any raide upon the Bordourers, or other malefactours or rebellious ſubjects. So as I have already ſaid, a good King, although he be above the Law, will ſubject and frame his actions ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, for examples ſake to his ſubjects, and of his own free-will, but not as ſubject or bound thereto. Since I have ſo clearely proved then out of the fundamentall laws &amp; practiſe of this Country, what right and power a King hath over his land and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, it is eaſie to be underſtood, what alleageance and obedience his lieges owe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him I meane alwayes of ſuch free Monarchies as our King is, and not of ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Kings, and much leſſe of ſuch ſort of governours, as the Dukes of <hi>Venice</hi> are, whoſe Ariſtocraticke, and limited government is nothing like to free Monarchies: although the malice of ſome writers hath not beene aſhamed to miſ-know any dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to be betwixt them. And if it be not lawfull to any particular Lords te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants or vaſſals, upon whatſoever pretext, to controle and diſplace their maſter, and Over-lord (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s is clearer no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Sun by all lawes of the world) how much leſſe may the ſubjects and vaſſals of the great Over-lord the King controle or diſplace him? And ſince in all inferiour judgments in the Land, the people may not upon any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects diſplace their Magiſtrates, although but ſubaltern: for the people of a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough, cannot diſplace their provoſt before the time of their election: nor in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall policy the flock can upon any pretence diſplace the paſtor, nor Iudge of him yea even the ſchoolemaſter cannot be diſplaced by his ſchollers. If theſe, cannot bee diſplaced for any occaſion or pretext by them that are ruled by them: much leſſe is it
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:158234:7"/>lawful upon any pretext to controle or diſplace the great Provoſt, and great Schoole-muſter of the whole land: except by inverting the order of all Law and reaſon, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded may bee made to command their commander, the judged to judge their Judge, and they that are governed, to governe their time about their Lord and gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. And the agreement of the Law of nature in this our ground with the Lawes and conſtitutions of God, and man, already alledged, will by two ſimilitudes eaſily appeare. The King towards his people is rightly compared to a Father of children, and to a head of a body compoſed of divers members. For as Fathers, the good Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Magiſtrates of the people of God acknowledged themſelves to their ſubjects And for all other well ruled common-wealths, the ſtile of <hi>Pater-Patria</hi> was ever, and is commonly uſed to Kings. And the proper office of a King towards his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects agrees very well with the office of the head towards the body, and all mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof. For from the head, being the ſeate of judgement, proceedeth the care and foreſight of guiding, and preventing all evill that may come to the body or any part thereof. The head cares for the body, ſo doth the King for his people. As the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe and direction flowes from the head, and the execution according thereunto belongs to the reſt of the members, every one according to their office: ſo is it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt a wiſe Princes, and his people. As the judgement comming from the head may not only imploy the members, every one in their own office, as long as they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for it, but likewiſe in caſe any of them be affected with any infirmity muſt care and provide for their remedy, in caſe it be curable; and if otherwiſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> cut them off for feare of infecting of the reſt: even ſo is it betwixt the Prince, and his people. And as there is ever hope of curing any diſeaſed member by the direction of the head, as long as it is whole; but by the contrary, if it hee troubled, all the members are partakers of that paine, ſo is it betwixt the Prince and his people.</p>
            <p>And now firſt for the fathers part (whoſe naturall love to his children I deſcribed in the firſt part of this my diſcourſe, ſpeaking of the duty that Kings owe to their ſubjects) conſider, I pray you what duty his children owe to him, and whether upon any pretext whatſoever, it wil not be thought monſtrous and unnaturall to his ſons, to riſe up againſt him, to controll him at their appetite, and when they think good, to ſley him, or to cut him off, and adopt to themſeves any other they pleaſe in his roome. Or can any pretence of wickedneſſe or rigour on his part bee a juſt excuſe for his children to put hand into him? And although we ſee by the courſe of nature, that love ever uſeth to deſcend more than to aſcend: in caſe it were true, that the Father hated and wronged the children never ſo much, will any man, endued with the leaſt ſpark of reaſon, think it lawfull for them to meete him with the line? Yea, ſuppoſe the Father were furiouſly following his ſons with a drawne ſword: is it lawfull for them to turne, and ſtrike againe, or make any reſiſtance but by flight? I thinke ſurely, if there were no more but the example of bruit beaſts, and unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable creatures, it may ſerve well inough to qualine and proove this my argument. We read often the piety that the Storkes have to their old and decayed parents. And generally we know, that there are many ſorts of beaſts and foules, that with vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and many bloudy ſtrokes will beate and baniſh their young ones from them, how ſoone they perceive them to be able to fend themſelves. But we never read or heard of any reſiſtance on their part, except among the Vipers: which proves ſuch perſons, as ought to be reaſonable creatures, and yet unnaturally follow this exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:158234:7"/>to bee indued with their viperous nature. And for the ſimilitude of the head and the body, it may very well fall out that the head will be forced to gaure cut off ſome rotten member (as I have already ſaid) to keep the reſt of the body in integrity. But what ſtate the body can be in, if the head, for any infirmity that can fall to it, be cut off, I leave it to the readers judgment. So as (to conclude this part) if the children may upon any pretext that can be imagined, lawfully riſe up againſt their Father, cut him off, and chooſe any other in his room; and if the body for the weale of it, may for any infirmity that can be in the head, ſtrike it off: then I cannot deny that the people may rebell, controle, and diſplace, or cut off their King at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and upon reſpects moving them. And whether theſe ſimilitudes repreſent bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the office of a King; or the offices of Maſters or Deacons of crafts, or Doctors in Phyſicke (which jolly compariſons are uſed by ſuch writers as maintaine the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary propoſition) I leave it alſo to the Readers diſcretion. And in eaſe any doubts might ariſe in any part of this treatiſe, (I will according to my promiſe) with the ſolution of 4. principall and moſt weighty doubts, that the adverſeries may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, conclude this diſcourſe. And firſt it is caſten up by diverſe, that employ their pens upon Apologiſts for rebel ſons and treaſons, that every man is borne to carry ſuch a natural zeale and duty to his common-wealth, as to his mother; that ſeeing it ſo rent, and deadly wounded, as whiles it will be by wicked &amp; tyrannous Kings, good Citizans will be forced, for the naturall zeale and duty they owe to their own native Country, to put their hard to work for freeing their common-wealth from ſuch a peſt. Whereunto I give two anſwers. Firſt, it is a ſure Axiom in <hi>Theologie,</hi> that evill ſhould not be done, that good may come of it. The wickedneſſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of the King can never make them that are ordained to be judged by him, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his Judges. And if it be not lawfull to a private man to revenge his private injury upon his private adverſary (ſince God hath only given the ſword to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate) how much leſſe is it lawful to the people, or any part of them (who all are but private men, the authority being alwayes with the Magiſtrate, as I have already proved) to take upon them the uſe of the ſword, whom to it belongs not, againſt the publike Magiſtrate, whom to only it belongeth. Next, in place of relieving the Common-wealth out of diſtreſſe (which is their only excuſe and colour) they ſhall heape double diſtreſſe and deſolation upon it: and ſo their rebellion ſhall procure the contrary effects that they pretend it for. For a King cannot be imagined to be ſo unruly and tyrannous, but the common-wealth will be kept in better order, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding thereof, by him, then it can be by his way-taking For firſt, all ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den mutations are perilous in common-wealths, hope being thereby given to all bare men to ſet up themſelves, and flie with other mens feathers, the reines being looſed to all the inſolencies that diſordered people can commit by hope of impani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, becauſe of the looſeneſſe of all things.</p>
            <p>And next, it is certaine that a King can never be ſo monſtrouſly vicious, but hee will generally favour juſtice, and maintaine ſome order, except in the particulars, wherein his inordinate luſts and paſſions carry him away: where by the contrary, no King being, nothing is unlawfull to none: And ſo the old opinion of the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers proves true, that better it is to live in a Common-wealth, where nothing is lawfull, then where all things are lawfull to all men: the Common-wealth at that time reſembling an un-daunted young horſe that hath caſten his ride. For as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:158234:8"/>the divine Poet <hi>Du Bartas</hi> ſaith: <hi>Better it were to ſuffer ſome diſorder in the eſtate, and ſome ſpots in the Common wealth, then, in pretending to reforme, utterly to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow the Republike.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond objection they ground upon the curſe, that hangs over the common wealth, where a wicked King raigneth. And, ſay they, there cannot be more accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table deed in the ſight of God, nor more dutifull to their common-weale, than to free the Country of ſuch a curſe, and vindicate to them their liberty, which is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall to all creatures to crave. Whereunto, for anſwer, I grant indeed, that a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked K. is ſent by God for a curſe to his people, and a plague for their ſins. But that it is lawfull to them to ſhake off that curſe at their owne hand, which God hath laid on them, that I deny, and may ſo doe juſtly. Will any deny that the King of <hi>Babel</hi> was a curſe to the people of God, as was plainely fore ſpoken and threatned unto them in the prophecy of their Captivity? And what was <hi>Nero</hi> to the Chriſtian Church in his time? And yet <hi>Ieremy</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> (as ye have elſe heard) commanded them not only to obey them, but heartily to pray for their welfare.</p>
            <p>It is certaine then (as I have already by the Law of God ſufficiently proved) that pattence, earneſt prayers to God, and amendment of their lives, are the onely lawfull meanes to move God to relieve them of that heavie curſe. As for vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to themſelves their owne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iberty, what lawfull power have they to revoke to themſelves again thoſe priviledges, which by their own conſent before were ſo ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put out of their hands? For if a Prince cannot juſtly bring back again to himſelfe the Priviledges once beſtowed by him or his predeceſſors upon any ſtate, or ranck of his ſubjects: how much leſſe may the ſubjects reive out of the Princes hand that ſuperiority, which he and his Predeceſſors have ſo long brooked over them? But the unhappy uniquity of the time, which hath oftentimes given over good ſucceſſe to their treaſonable attempts, furniſheth them the ground of their third objection. For, ſay they, the fortunate ſucceſſe that God hath ſo oft given to ſuch enterpriſes, proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth plainly by the practice, that God favoured the juſtneſſe of their quarrell. To the which I anſwer, that it is true indeed, that all the ſucceſſe of battels, as well as other worldly things, lyeth only in Gods hand. And therfore it is that in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture he takes to himſelfe the God of Hoſts. But upon that generall to conclude, that he ever gives victory to the juſt quarrell, would prove the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> and diverſe other neighbour enemies of the people of GOD, to have oftimes had the juſt quarrell againſt the people of GOD, in reſpect of the many Victories they obtained againſt them. And by that ſame argument they had juſt quarrell againſt the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ke of God. For they wan it in the field, and kept it long priſoner in the Country. As likewiſe by all good writers, as well Theologues, as other the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lls and ſingular combates are diſallowed: which are only made upon pretence that God will kith thereby the juſtice of the quarrell. For we muſt conſider that the innocent party is not innocent before God. And therefore God will make oft times them that have the wrong ſide, revenge juſtly his quarrell; and when he hath done, caſt his ſcourge on the fire: as hee oftentimes did to his owne people ſtirring up and ſtrengthening their enemies, while they were humbled in his ſight, and then deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered them in their hands. So God, as the great Iudge may iuſtly puniſh his deputy, and for his rebellion againſt him, ſtir up his rebels to meete him with the like. And when it is done, the part of the inſtrument is no better than the divels part is in temp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting and torturing ſuch as God committeth to him as his hangman to do. Therefore as I ſaid in the beginning, it is oft times a very deceiveable argument, to iudge of the cauſe by the event.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:158234:8"/>
And the laſt objection is grounded upon the mutuall paction and adſtipulation (as they call it) betwixt the King and his people, at the time of his Coronation. For there ſay they, there is a mutuall paction, and contract bound up, and ſworne betwixt the King, and the people. Whereupon it followeth, that if the one part of the contract or the Indent be broken upon the Kings ſide, the people are no longer bound to keepe their part of it, but are thereby freed of their oath. For (ſay they) a contract betwixt two parties of all law frees the one party if the other breake unto him. As to this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract alledged made at the coronation of a King, although I deny any ſuch contract to be made then, eſpecially containing ſuch a clauſe irritant as they alledge: yet I confeſſe, that a King at his coronation, or at the entry to his Kingdome, willingly promiſeth to his people, to diſcharge honorably and truely the office given him by God over them. But preſuming that thereafter hee breake his promiſe unto them never ſo inexcuſable, the queſtion is, who ſhould be judge of the breake, giving unto them this contract were made unto them never ſo ſicker, according to their alleageance. I think no man that hath but the ſmalleſt entrance in the civill Law, will doubt that of all law either civill or municipall of any nation a contract cannot be thought broken by the one party, and ſo the other likewiſe to be freed therefro except that firſt a lawful tryall &amp; cognition be had by the ordinary Iudge of the breakers thereof. Elſe every man may be both party and judge in his own cauſe: which is abſurd once to be thought. Now in this contract (I ſay) betwixt the King and his people, God is doubtleſſe the only Iudge, both becauſe to him only the King muſt make count of his adminiſtration (as is oft ſaid before) as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by the oath in the Coronation, God is made judge and revenger of the breakers. For in his preſence, as only judge of oaths, all oaths ought to be made. Then ſince God is the onely judge betwixt the two parties contractors, the cognition and revenge muſt only appertaine to him. It followes therefore of neceſſity, that God muſt firſt give ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence upon the King that breaketh, before the people can think themſelves freed of their oath What juſtice then is it, that the party ſhall be both judge and party, uſurping up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelfe the office of God, may by this argument eaſily appare: And ſhall it lye in the hands of headleſſe multitude, when they pleaſe to weary off ſubjection, to caſt off the yoke of government that God hath ſaid upon them; to judge and puniſh him, by whom they ſhould be judged and puniſhed; and in that caſe, wherein by their vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence they kithe themſelves to be moſt paſſionate parties, to uſe the office of an ungra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Iudge or Arbiter? Nay, to ſpeake truly of that caſe, as it ſtands betwixt the King and his people, none of them ought to judge of the others breake. For conſidering rightly the two parties at the time of their mutuall promiſe, the King is the one party, and the whole people in one body are the other party And therefore ſince it is certaine, that a King, in caſe ſo it ſhould fall out, that his people in one body had rebelled againſt him, the ſhould not in that caſe, as thinking himſelfe free of his promiſe and oath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come an utter enemy, and practice the wreak of his whole people and native Country: although he ought juſtly to puniſh the principall authors and bellowes of that univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall rebellion: how much leſſe then ought the people that are alwayes ſubject unto him, and naked of al authority (on their part) preſſe to judge and overthrow him? other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the people, as the one party contracters, ſhal no ſooner challenge the King as brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, but he as ſoone ſhall judge them as breakers: ſo as, the victors making the tyners the traitours (as our proverb is) the party ſhall aye become both judge and party in his owne particular, as I have already ſaid.</p>
            <p>And it is here likewiſe to bee noted that the duty and allegeance, which the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſweareth to their Prince is not only bound to themſelves, but likewiſe to their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full heires and poſterity, the lineall ſucceſſion of Crowns being begun among the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, and happily continued in diverſe Chriſtian common wealths. So as no ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection either of hereſie, or whatſoever private ſtatute or Law may free the people from their oath given to their King. and his ſucceſſion, eſtabliſhed by the old funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Lawes of the kingdom. For, as he is their heritable Over-lord, and ſo by birth,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:158234:9"/>not by any right in the coronation, commeth to his Crowne; it is a like unlawfull (the crowne ever ſtanding full) to diſplace him that ſucceedeth thereto, as to eject the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. For at the very moment of the expiring of the King raigning, the neareſt and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full heire entreth in his place. And ſo to refuſe him, or intrude another; is not to hold out uncomming in; but to expell, and put out their righteous King. And I truſt at this time whole France acknowledgeth the ſuperſtitious rebellion of the liguers; who upon pretence of hereſie, by force of armes held ſo long out, to the great deſolation of their whole Country, their native and righteous King from poſſeſſing of his own crown and naturall kingdom. Not that by all this former diſcourſe of mine, &amp; Apology for Kings, I meane that whatſoever errours and intollerable abhominations a Soveraigne Prince commit, he ought to eſcape all puniſhment, as if thereby the world were only ordained for Kings, and they without controlement to turne it upſide down at their pleaſure But by the contrary, by remitting them to God (who is their only ordinary Iudge) I remit them to the foreſt and ſharpeſt ſchoole. Maſter that can be deviſed for them. For the further a King is preferred by God above all other rankes and degrees of men, and the higher that his feate is above theirs, the greater is his obligation to his maker. And therefore in caſe hee forget himſelfe (his unthankfulneſſe being in the ſame meaſure of height the ſadder and ſharper will his correction be: and according to the greatneſſe of the height he is in, the waight of his ſale will recompence the ſame. For the further that any perſon is obliged to God, his offence becom and growes ſo much the greates, then it would bee in any other. Ioves thunder-claps light oftner, and ſorer upon the high &amp; ſtately Oakes, then on the low and ſupple willow trees. And the higheſt bench is ſliddrieſt to ſit upon. Neither is it ever heard that any King forgets himſelfe towards God, or in his vocation; but God with the greatnes of the plague revengeth the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his ingratitude Neither think I by the force &amp; argument of this my diſcourſe ſo to perſwade the people, that none will hereafter be raiſed up, and rebell againſt wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Princes. But remitting to the juſtice and providence of God to ſtirre up ſuch ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges as pleaſeth him, for uniſhment of wicked Kings (who made the very vermine and filthy duſt of the earth to bridle the inſolency of proud Pharaoh) my only purpoſe and it tention in this treatiſe is to perſwade, as far as lyeth in me, by theſe ſure and infallible grounds, all ſuch good Chriſtian Readers, as beare not only the naked name of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, but kith the fruits thereof in their daily forme of life, to keepe their hearts and hands free from ſuch monſtrous and unnaturall rebellions, whenſoever the wickednes of a Prince ſhall procures the ſame at Gods hands: that, when it ſhall pleaſe God to caſt ſuch ſuch ſcourges of Princes, and inſtruments of his fury in the fire, ye may ſtand up with cleane hands, and unſpotted conſciences, having proved your ſelves in all your actions true chriſtians toward God, and dutifull ſubjects towards your King, having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the judgment and puniſhment of all his wrongs to him, whom to only of right it appertaineth. But craving at God, and hoping that God ſhall continue his bleſſing with us, in not ſending ſuch fearefull deſolation, I heartily wiſh our Kings behaviour ſo to be, and continue among us, as our God in earth, and loving Father, indued with ſuch properties as I deſcribed a King in the firſt part of this Treatiſe. And that ye (my deare Country men and charitable readers) may preſſe by all meanes to procure the proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and welfare of your King: that, as he muſt on the one part thinke a I his earthly felicity and happineſſe grounded upon your weale; caring more for himſelfe for your ſake then for his own, thinking himſelfe only ordained for your weale; ſuch holy and happy emulation may ariſe betwixt him, and you, as his care for your quietneſſe, and your care for his honour and preſervation, may in all your actions daily ſtrive toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: that the Land may thinke themſelves bleſſed with ſuch a King, and the King may thinke Himſelfe moſt happie in ruling over ſo loving and obedient Sukjects.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
